[{"question":"Sewage purification is done by:","a":"Microbes","b":"Fertilisers","c":"Antibiotics","d":"Antiseptics","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Methanogenic bacteria present in:","a":"(a) Anaerobic sludge","b":"(b) Rumen (a part of stomach) of cattle","c":"(c) Both (a) and (b)","d":"(d) None of these","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Acetic acid is produced with the help of","a":"Albuco species","b":"(b) Acetobacter species","c":"(c) Aspergillus species","d":"(d) Lactobacillus species","hint":"(b) The bacterium, Acetobacter acel is used Forthe production of acetic acid in industries. It is mainly used in pharmaceutical industries, colouring agent, insecticides ","correct":"d"},{"question":"Lichen that yields antibiotic is:","a":"(a) Ampicillin","b":"(b) Oxacillin","c":"(c) Both (a) and (b)","d":"(d) Tetracycline","hint":"(c) Ampicillin and oxacillin are modified  antibiotics and once known assemisynthetic antibiotics.","correct":"c"},{"question":"Antibiotics are mostly got from:","a":"(a) Fungi","b":"(b) Virus","c":"(c) Bacteria","d":"(d) Cyanobacteria","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which antibiotic inhibits peptide bond formation?","a":"(a) Streptomycin","b":"(b) Tetracyclin","c":"(c) Chloramphenicol","d":"(d) Neomycin","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"7. Penicillin inhibits bacterial multiplication","a":"(a) checks RNA synthesis.","b":"(b) checks DNA synthesis.","c":"(c) destroys chromatin formation.","d":"(d) inhibits cell wall formation.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"8.  Pasteurisation is heating at:","a":"(a) 120°C for 60 minutes","b":"(b) 60-63°C for 30 minutes","c":"(c) 70°C for 60 minutes","d":"(d) 80°C for 30 minutes","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following is not an antibiotic?","a":"(a) Griseofulvin","b":"(b) Cephalosporin","c":"(c) Citric acid","d":"(d) Streptomycin","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"10.  Probiotics are:","a":"(a) live microbial food supplement.","b":"(b) cancer inducing microbes.","c":"new kind of food allergens.","d":"(d) safe antibiotics.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"11. Streptokinase, used as a 'clot buster' is obtained  from:","a":"(a) Streptococcus","b":"(b) Staphylococcus","c":"(c) Lactobacillus","d":"(d) Saccharomyces","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"12. Secondary sludge uses:","a":"(a) gravitational sedimentation","b":"(b) primary clarifier","c":"(c) non-biodegradable materials","d":"(d) micro-organism to consume waste organic","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"13. Indicator of water pollution is:","a":"(a) E. coll","b":"Chlorella","c":"(c) Beggiatoa","d":"(d) Ulothric","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Germinating barley is employed for preparation","a":"(a) Wine","b":"(b) Beer","c":"(c) Lactic acid","d":"(d) Cheese","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Most widely used enzyme in detergents is:","a":"(a) Amylases","b":"(b) Lipases","c":"(c) Proteases","d":"(d) Glucoisomerases","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Passage of effluents into oxidation tank is for:","a":"(a) Primary treatment","b":"(b) Secondary treatment","c":"(c) Tertiary treatment","d":"(d) Both (a) and (b)","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Enzymes are immobilised through:","a":"(a) covalently attaching to solid support","b":"(b) cross-linking","c":"(c) entrapping in gel","d":"(d) All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"18. Cheese and yogurt are products of:","a":"(a) Pasteurisation","b":"(b) Fermentation","c":"(c) Dehydration","d":"(d) Distillation","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"19. Citric acid is obtained from:","a":"(a) Aspergillus niger","b":"(b) Rhizobium nigricans.","c":"(c) Penicillium citrinum","d":"(d) Lactobacillus bulgaricus","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"20.  Baculoviruses are excellent pathogens  for","a":"(a) species-specific narrow spectrum pesticidal applications","b":"(b) species-specific broad spectrum pesticidal application ","c":"(c) species-specific narrow spectrum insecticidal application ","d":"(d) species-specific broad spectrum insecticidal application ","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"21. Human insulin is being commercially produced","a":"(a) Rhizobium","b":"(b) Saccharomyces","c":"(b) Escherichia","d":"(d) Mycobacterium","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The amount of oxygen required by the microbes","a":"(a) Chemical oxygen demand","b":"(b) Biochemical oxygen demand","c":"(c) Total oxygen demand","d":"(d) Dissolved oxygen","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"23. Enzyme immobilisation is:","a":"(a) conversion of an active enzyme into  inactive","b":"(b) providing enzyme with protective covering","c":"(c) changing a soluble enzyme into insoluble state.","d":"(d) changing pH so that enzyme is not able to carry out its function.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"24. In sewage treatment process, which part of  decomposer bacteria is recycled into starting of","a":"(a) Cyclic treatment","b":"(b) Primary treatment","c":"(c) Tertiary treatment","d":"(d) Activated sludge treatment","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"A lake with an inflow of Domestic  sewagein organic waste may result in:","a":"(a) drying of the lake very soon due to algal bloom.","b":"(b) an increased production of fish due to lot  enzyme  of nutrients.","c":"C death of fish due to lack of oxygen.","d":"(d) increased population of aquatic food web organisation.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Sewage purification is done by:","a":"Microbes","b":"Fertilisers","c":"Antibiotics","d":"Antiseptics","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Cider is prepared by:","a":"action of Lactobacillus on milk.","b":"action of Saccharomyces on apple juice.","c":"(c) action of Saccharomyces on cane sugar.","d":"action of Bacillus on ramie.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Activated sludge has the ability to settle quickly this enables it","a":"(a) be rapidly pumped back from sedimentation to aeration tank.","b":"(b) absorb pathogenic bacteria while sinking  (b) species-specific broad spectrum pesticidal  to the bottom of the settling-tank.","c":"(c) anaerobically digested and be discarded.","d":"(d) absorb colloidal organic matter.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Jatropha is a","a":"Biodiesel crop","b":"Biopetro crop","c":"Fibre crop","d":"Food crop","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Consider the following statements about,secondary sewage treatment. Which of thestatements given are correct?","a":"(i) In secondary treatment useful aerobicmicrobes grow rapidly and form flocs of bacterial and fungal filaments in a mesh- like structure.","b":"(ii) The growing microbes consume organicmatter reducing the BOD after which the  (d) Dissolved oxygen  effluent is passed into settling tank.","c":"In settling tank, the bacterial floes settle and the sediment is called activated sludge.","d":"(a) (i), (ii), (ii) and (iv) (b) (i), (ii), (iv) and (v)(c) (ii), (iii), (iv) and (v)(d) (i), (ii), (i), (iv) and","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Pyrethrin is a common ingredient of","a":"Mosquito coils ","b":"(B) Fly Sprays","c":"(c) Mosquito mats ","d":"(D) All Of These","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Thurioside is an:","a":"Insecticide","b":"Fungicide","c":"Antibiotic","d":"Weedicide","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The free-living fungus Trichoderma can Be used for  ","a":"killing insects","b":"biological control of plant diseases","c":"controlling butterfly caterpillars","d":"producing antibiotics","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"A genetically engineered micro-organism usedsuccessfully in bioremediation of oil spills is a  species of","a":"Pseudomonas","b":"Trichoderma","c":"Xanthomonas","d":"Bacillus","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Viral pesticide used against gypsy moths is:","a":"NPV","b":"Nosema locustae","c":"Fusarium","d":"Beauveria bassiana","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Identify the microorganism which is commerciallyexploited as the source of bioinsecticides?","a":"Chrysanthemum cinerariifolium","b":"Phytophthora palmivora","c":"Bacillus thuringiensis","d":"Both (a) and (e)","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Methane content of biogas is:","a":"(a) 24.6%   ","b":"(B) 55.8%","c":"(C) 8%","d":"(D) 4%","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"For Biogas Production Besides Dung, An Extensive  Use Of Which Weed Is Recommended In Our Country?","a":"Mangifera Indica","b":"Hydrilla","c":"Eichhornia crassipes","d":"Solanum","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"IPM (Integrated Pest Management) involves:","a":"Tissue culture","b":"Biological control","c":"Biofertilisers","d":"Confusion technique","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following is the pair of biofertilisers?","a":"Azolla and blue green algae","b":"Nostoc and legume","c":"Rhizobium and grasses","d":"Salmonella & E. coli","hint":"","correct":"a"}]